Someone once came up
to me at a
business networking event and
told me that the
60 second pitch that
I'd just stood up
and given to the
room was the worst
they had ever seen.
And he was right.
My presenting skills were
shambolic. But I didn't
care. I just thought
whatever, presenting doesn't matter
that much. And I
was so blind to
my massive problem, I
didn't realise that nobody
in the room took
me seriously and eventually
I was asked to
leave the group. Fast
forward seven years later
and there's a message
from someone from Mr
Beast's production team in
my DMs. The message
was not what I
expected though. It said,
Hey Ed, I really
like what you do.
I just wanted to
reach out and ask
what is it about
the way you present
that makes me trust
you so much? They
went on to explain
that for some reason
they just felt like
they could trust me
more than other creators
and they couldn't understand
how I'd created this
impact on them. So
in this video, I'm
going to show you
how to level up
your presenting to blow
up your credibility and
trust, even if you're
a flipping embarrassment or
in denial that you
don't need to improve
your presentation just like
I was. I'm going
to teach you the
presentation, the tricks that
will remove any concerns
with your viewers that
you're nothing other than
a stand up gal
or guy. And I'm
going to help you
break down your style
by breaking down all
kinds of creators and
the way they build
trust on screen. But
first, I need to
tell you a little
secret. So you might
be sitting there thinking
to yourself, I'm good
at presenting. I can
move on to the
next video. But just
consider this. I know
multiple educational YouTube creators
with millions of subscribers
and massive personal brands
who hire people to
teach them presenting skills
still. But it goes
deeper. They pull in
acting coaches, some hire
singing coaches to help
them improve the power
of their own voice.
The top 1 %
are just not sitting
there going, presenting, completed
that. They're going, how
do I get an
upper hand on everyone
else? And you should
too, because the way
you present yourself is
a massive percentage of
your overall communication on
YouTube. So skip this
at your own peril.
Okay, so let's start
with how I managed
to build trust with
the way I present
and why you definitely
do not want to
do what I do.
So my secret to
pulling this off is
actually pretty simple. When
I was 18, I
was a professional singer.
I was a singer,
but I was also
a singer. I was
a professional singer on
YouTube. So that was
the first step. Then
at 18, I started
making videos, and everyone
used to laugh at
me for it. As
time moved on, I
kept making them, and
in 2009, I went
to Japan and made
a vlog. I uploaded
it, and I was
met with a load
of laughter again. Comments
were like, what are
you doing walking around
Japan talking to yourself
in the streets? So
I just deleted the
video out of shame.
A year later, I
went away with my
friends and kept filming,
but this time in
the edit, I did
something very different. I
focused on one thing.
Only ever showing clips
where people were enjoying
themselves. I'd notice that
when I saw someone
having fun on camera,
It just made me
feel good. So I
launched this video and
the comments were so
different and everyone was
like, this looks great.
And messages from people
saying, Ed, can I
come away with you
please next time? And
that's how I developed
my film booth style.
I basically came to
the conclusion that people
like watching other people
have fun because it
fills a void in
an otherwise mundane part
of their day. It's
infectious and it's welcoming.
So that's what I
based my film booth
presenting style on. I
just simply present in
a way that makes
it look and sound
like I'm enjoying myself.
And it worked. But
deep down, I'm not.
I hate this. But
how do you do
that? Well, it's so
simple. The first thing
you do is you
just smile more often.
It's actually proven by
science that when someone
smiles at you, you
smile back. And researchers
say that your brain
tells your facial muscles
to mimic the other
person's expression. It's basically
an extreme version of
putting yourself in someone
else's shoes. And what's
even crazier is the
feeling of smiling reminds
you of past experiences
where you've smiled too.
So a simple smile
will give your viewers
a happy feeling. But
on the flip side.
Just think back to
when you were a
kid and you went
around your friend's house.
You'd have one friend
where you'd knock on
the door and their
mum would answer and
look at you and
just grunt. And then
just let you in
and you'd feel super
unwelcome. And then you'd
have another friend who'd
be like, oh, amazing
to see you. Come
on in. Go in
the back and play
with the boys. I've
got some chocolate coming
on the way. But
don't go in my
second bedroom drawer. A
smile or a frown
or a grumpy expression
can take us back
to these moments. So
just keep in mind
that your aura is
giving off a lot
of signals to your
viewers. So that's the
secret of my own
film booth presenting style.
And this brings us
on to why you
should not mimic me.
So imagine YouTube is
your real life personality
plus 20%. In person,
I'm pretty much what
you see on camera.
Or so I've been
told by the people
I've met who have
seen me on camera,
but a watered down
version. What that means
is if you're not
like me, you shouldn't
try to present like
me. The whole make
it smile approach could
be the exact opposite
of what people like
about you. So what
you need to do
instead is create a
persona that is true
to you. A persona
will enable you to
feel more confident in
yourself as well. Because
it's not just about
you. It's your persona.
Beyonce has Sasha Fierce,
a character she made
up because Beyonce is
not as confident as
she wanted to be.
So she came up
with a woman who
had no fear and
the second she steps
on the stage, that
version of her takes
over. Ed from film
booth is the same.
I mean I talk
like this when I'm
being normal. But when
Ed from film booth
takes over, the show
begins and everything's just
way more dramatic. So
we need to work
out your style and
your persona so you
can come across as
confident and likeable to
the right people and
build your trust. To
do that, I'd like
to introduce you to
my partner, the best
friend, the best friend
of my life. We're
going to start by
looking at two types
of youtube creators and
the three levels within
them. So let's start
by looking at the
two types of creators.
Let's start by looking
at the two types
of creators. The first
type is the authentic
type. Here's a few
examples. So we have
Nisha, she presents like
this. If you've ever
complained about not being
able to save enough
money, not being able
to pay your bills
on time, or feeling
demotivated to act on
your finances, once you
do this, a huge
weight will be lifted
off your shoulders. The
wizard, Liz, she talks
to camera like this.
The goal shouldn't be
that this guy is
obsessed with you. The
goal should be that
you are obsessed with
yourself. Hamza, who talks
like this. And so
we asked for some
advice on how to
get over some mistakes
that he had made.
And maybe this is
relevant to you. Maybe
there's a mistake that
you've already been thinking
about since you clicked
on this video, which
you did, you know,
a little while ago,
and it still bothers
you to this day.
It's just a mindset
change that you need.
Danco, like this. Here's
how you get ahead
of 99 % of
people in 6 to
12 months. And of
course, Casey, who sounded
like this. I think
I spend 50 %
of my time procrastinating,
50 % of my
time not working. And
then the other 50
% of my time
frantically working to make
up for the time
that I spent not
working. All of these
creators have a very
raw and real style.
There's no bells or
whistles. It just feels
like it's your friend
chatting with you. And
you kind of get
the feeling they actually
care about you. And
this is very hard
to pull off if
it doesn't come that
naturally to you. The
second option is the
performer. So we have
me, who sounds like
this. Or Mosey, who
presents like this. I
f***ing guarantee you that
you will be making
more than people who
have four -year degrees.
You'll probably start making
money by the end
of the first year.
Tom Scott, who presents
like this. If you're
boarding a big aircraft,
the kind of large
Boeing or Airbus that
goes across the Atlantic,
you'll probably get on
and off the plane
using a jet bridge.
That's the movable, extendable
corridor that connects the
terminal to the plane.
Matt Watson, who sounds
like this. I'm at
Tesla's Gigafactory in Austin,
Texas,
for the unveiling of
the first customer card.
The new Tesla Cybertruck.
You're going to hear
on YouTube all the
time that the authentic
style is coming back.
Bulls**t. It's always been
there. People will blow
up and grow quickly,
but we cannot take
their style and say,
oh, this is the
one thing viewers want
now. It just doesn't
work like that. And
here's the head of
the YouTube algorithm backing
me up. So that's
the two levels, authentic
and performer. And now
on these two levels,
we have a spectrum.
We have quiet confidence
and then confidence. Basically,
it doesn't matter what
you do. You need
to appear confident on
camera. As this builds
trust. But you also
want to think about
where you fit on
this spectrum. So an
authentic and very quiet,
confident based presenter is
probably the least offensive
type of YouTuber in
the world. They're all
nicey -nicey and squeaky
clean. And they never
really say anything that's
polarizing. And they try
to keep everyone happy.
And they can get
millions of views doing
this. The thing is,
oh my gosh, they're
so boring. Just have
a strong opinion, why
don't you? I personally
just don't enjoy watching
this type of video,
but millions of others
do. Some examples of
a quiet, confident, authentic
presenter, after I've just
said all those horrible
things about them, are
Ali Abdaal, Nisha, Matt
Novella. Now I should
probably say I think
these guys are legends.
But for me, I
don't watch presenters of
this nature for my
own enjoyment. I do
it for the love
of the art. Now
you might be the
same or you might
disagree with me, but
that's the nature of
YouTube. Everyone has their
own preference. Then on
the other side of
the spectrum, on the
confident side, we have
Dan Coe. So Dan
gives you a lot
more tough love in
an authentic way. The
Wizard Liz, most of
all. He motivates the
butt off of you.
And then you've got
Cody Sanchez, who's a
really powerful woman with
big conviction. Emily D.
Baker is the mum
that opens the door
and welcomes you with
arms wide open. And
then this guy, Nico
Leonard, who makes a
load of reaction content
to watches. He's just
giving his opinion, but
he's often super convicted
in his outrageous statements,
and people love him
for it. Today I'm
creating the ultimate watch
collection for poor people.
The higher up the
scale you go, the
more confidence you exude,
and usually the more
polarising people are too.
And what that means
is people love or
hate those creators, but
the ones further up
the scale are the
ones that I personally
prefer to watch. Then
we have the performative
creators, and the same
scale applies. So with
quiet confidence, we have
Tom Scott. He's not
polarising. He's easy to
watch. And he kind
of feels like the
best teacher you had
at school, but he's
got some showmanship to
him. Then we have
Mr Who's the Boss,
who puts on an
amazing show every video.
Then in the middle,
we kind of have
Homozy. Then we have
the ultimate confident person
who puts on an
epic show. And look,
you don't have to
be a great showman.
You don't have to
like this man. But
if you want an
example of how to
blow up to become
world famous, nobody has
ever done it like
him. It's Andrew Tate.
Okay, so there's the
two types of presenters
and a scale. Where
do you want to
fit on it? Well,
to me, that's not
actually much of a
choice. We kind of
land on our style.
Like, if you're not
a confident polarising person,
you probably won't be
able to just magic
that up on camera.
And the same in
reverse. That's called acting,
although it's not impossible.
So now what I'm
going to do is
help you build your
style by giving you
some exercises to try
out. And when you
do them, you're going
to see your persona
appear. What I need
you to do first,
though, is go and
shut your door and
then set up a
camera or a phone
or a webcam. It
doesn't really matter. You
just need to be
able to record yourself
and watch it back
really quickly. No need
for lighting or anything
fancy. And nobody else
is ever going to
see this. All right,
so the first thing
we're going to look
at is true no
matter if you are
quite authentic or a
confident performer. Every single
person who's successful on
YouTube does this, apart
from Matt D 'Avella.
Damn it, Matt D
'Avella fit my narrative.
And I have them
doing it on screen
right now. Can you
see the pattern here?
Every single one of
these people is expressing
themselves with their body
language and their hand
movements, which will feel
very unnatural to start.
But I'm going to
give you some tricks
to master this and
you'll look slicker than
a bar of soap
in the shower. So
the first step, all
I want you to
do is present a
line or two of
any script you have
and put your hands
here in position one,
which is just kind
of by your side
of your lap, and
then bring them up
to position two, which
is here. Now, if
you're on a table,
it would look like
this. Position one, position
two. So here's an
example of a line
of a script. Without
this. Okay, so the
first thing we're going
to look at is
true, no matter if
you're quiet, authentic or
a confident performer. Every
single person who is
successful on YouTube does
this, apart from Matt
D 'Avella. Damn it,
Matt D 'Avella fit
my narrative. Now, what
I'm going to do
is go to position
one and position two.
Okay, so the first
thing we look at
is true, no matter
if you are a
quiet, authentic or a
confident performer. Every single
person who is successful
on YouTube does this,
apart from Matt D
'Avella. Damn it, Matt
D 'Avella fit my
narrative. You see the
difference there? So just
record yourself here. You're
saying your line now
and bring your hands
from position one to
position two. That's kind
of it. Don't worry,
we're going to build
on this. Pause, do
it. Do it now.
Okay, good. So now
you've done that, we're
going to level it
up a little bit.
So think about the
words you're saying and
then how you might
act those words out
in sign language. So
some really simple ways
to do this are,
if you list numbers
in your video, use
your fingers to show
them. So if you
say, five tips to
make the best Battenberg
cake of all time,
it makes a big
difference. Then the next
little trick is really
simple. So if you're
like, never add sugar
to flatbread, flour first.
Imagine how you communicate
that with only your
hands. You'd be like,
don't do it. So
we can use these
hand motions to bring
our content to life.
And then another trick
I use all the
time is when I
count my words. So
if I want something
to sink in, it's
like I'm bonking my
words on the head.
For example, always add
milk first. Okay, so
go and try this
for yourself now. Do
it like four or
five times. Try and
throw all of these
things. It's going to
feel really weird to
start. And just try
different hand movements and
bonky words on the
head. Go all loosey
goosey and throw your
arms about. What will
happen is eventually you're
going to see a
version of yourself that
you're really going to
like. And this will
all become second nature.
But just don't write
this off when it
looks a bit weird
the first five or
ten times you try
it. So let's add
them all to my
example and we'll see
what I look like.
Okay, so the first
thing we're going to
look at is true
no matter if you
are a quiet, authentic
or a confident performer.
Every single person who
is successful on YouTube
does this apart from
Matt D 'Avella. Come
here, Matt D 'Avella.
Fit my narrative. You're
basically conducting your words
and you're going to
see this everywhere. Even
people like Nisha who
cried and had to
crop off her hands
because she brings the
camera in too close
are doing this out
of shot because it
actually impacts your voice
and the tone of
it too. And this
will build trust and
confidence as well. Okay,
so the next tool
we're going to use
is a technique that
I've used on hundreds
of people in my
old production company. And
I took them from
never having presented ever
to looking like they've
been presenting years in
a matter of minutes.
And I call it
Panto Mode. So a
pantomime in the UK
is this kids play.
The actors in it
are always really over
the top. And what
we established was that
the camera sucks about
20 % of the
life out of you.
So in order to
appear a bit more
natural on camera, you
need to put 20
% more energy back
into your presenting and
into your voice and
into your body language.
So now what I
want you to do
is take a line
from one of your
scripts and record yourself
presenting it. Just read
it off the script.
Don't worry about trying
to memorize it. This
is actually very important
for voiceovers too. And
then what I need
you to do is
say the line multiple
times. The first time,
I want you to
present it with 150
% energy. Seriously, I
need you to try
and look like an
absolute fool doing this.
It's going to make
you feel really uncomfortable.
But trust me on
this. I want to
just mention one thing.
More energy does not
mean shouting. And then
try it at 130%,
then 110, then 100,
then 90%, then 80.
And then do it
again, but put more
emphasis on one word
in the sentence with
the same level of
energy. Ideally, we would
put emphasis on the
words that are more
important. The ones the
viewers really need to
pay attention to. See,
just did it that
then. So I'll demonstrate
now. We're not going
to do all of
them because we'll get
bored, but just enough
to give you the
idea. Okay, so this
is 150 % energy
of a line in
my script. The more
energy you use when
you present, the more
engaged your viewers will
come, but you have
to find the right
balance for your tone.
Okay, and then this
is 120 % energy.
The more energy you
use when you present,
the more engaged your
viewers will come, but
you have to find
the right balance for
your tone. And then
this is 90 %
energy. The more energy
you use when you
present, the more engaged
your viewers will come,
but you have to
find the right balance
for your tone. Okay,
so it's a big
difference, right? So go
and shoot all of
yours, then watch them
back. And what's likely
to happen is this.
You're going to watch
one of those and
go, Wow! That's how
I want to come
across! And you'll have
found your energy. It's
usually around the 120
% mark if you
get the body language
and emphasis right, but
just keep in mind
You probably won't get
it right the first
few times you do
this. So don't write
it off as nonsense
I'm teaching you to
drive an f1 car.
You can't expect to
win your first race
okay, so the next
thing I want you
to get comfortable with
is The pause so
he cut a lot
of these out in
the YouTube world But
what I found was
when I was learning
to present I thought
I had to keep
talking and if I
stopped or I stumbled
I'd look bad actually
when you pause You
look composed and pausing
will eliminate arms and
ours, which is basically
your brain saying say
something So try your
line again, but put
in a pause at
a point that feels
natural and give an
example Okay So the
first thing we're going
to look at is
true no matter if
you are a quiet
authentic or a confident
performer Every single person
who is successful on
YouTube Part from Matt
de Vela. Damn it,
Matt de Vela! Fit
my narrative. So once
you've played around with
that We're gonna move
on to something I
call sneaky mode So
when I started presenting
I kind of started
to never I didn't
know what I was
doing and I was
like, oh, I'm gonna
nail this whole panto
mode thing and it
was working really well
The thing is your
script suddenly switches to
a serious moment being
all happy clappy It
doesn't work and I
was presenting in panto
mode for lines like
this And then they
got hit by a
lorry and their seven
children had to fend
for themselves on the
streets for the rest
of their lives There's
a bit of a
clash, right? And when
we get into storytelling
in the later modules
the tone of your
voice is going to
play a really big
part in it Now
to fix this I
accidentally came up with
sneaky mode So when
I started out? I
used to film videos
in my parents garage
and one day I
really Needed to make
a video but my
mum and her friend
were standing outside and
I felt so embarrassed
to be in there
presenting So I just
decided to hit record
and tried to present
so the people outside
the room couldn't actually
hear me The microphone
could and then I
watched it back and
I was like damn.
This is really good
I sounded like I
cared. Ha just used
it on you there.
Did you notice the
difference? So what you
do is you soften
your voice like you
don't want people in
the room next to
you to hear It's
almost like a loud
whisper and it's amazing
for those intimate moments
In fact If you
watch a film booth
video back now you're
gonna notice I just
switch between Panto mode
and sneaky mode all
of the time and
that's pretty much all
I do if it's
a vulnerable moment I
go into sneaky mode
if it's a motivational
moment sneaky mode can
work too, but if
it's excitement and fun
It's panto mode baby.
So go and take
your line now and
try it in sneaky
mode Maybe change the
line to something more
vulnerable and just see
what happens All right
So now I'm gonna
give you a few
more things to consider
with you presenting and
you're gonna see politicians
use this a lot
Especially Donald Trump because
he knows exactly how
to make his body
language do the talking
for him So the
first of these things
is something you need
to avoid and I'll
tell you why in
a minute I'll tell
you why because it
will take you back
to when you're a
wee laddie or lassie
who had done something
wrong and you Were
getting told off by
your parents and I'm
doing it to you
right now. Don't point
at your viewers just
comes across as angry
Unless that is of
course your desired result
now the next presenting
hack I'm also doing
right now and what
it does is it
it makes us come
across as open and
more honest Marcus Brownlee
uses this a lot
too as well as
slimy politicians who lie
to us all of
the time and The
way they do that
is by simply opening
up their hands. All
right, so guess what?
I'm doing the next
one now too And
I promise you this
it will give you
more authority and make
you look more certain
There's no denying it
and you do this
by just putting your
hands down Which is
crazy effective for emphasizing
a key point in
your video But at
the same time you
can use it to
calm things down a
minute We've all had
a few drinks All
I'd say is be
careful with this because
it can come across
as a little bit
negative but not as
negative as this I'd
probably avoid closed fists
at all costs Although
it can show determination
at some points And
finally we get on
to what? I consider
to be the strangest
thing ever about presenting
YouTube videos and I
need to show you
why you need to
avoid doing this So
if people do this
They are instinctively protecting
their organs the same
when they cross their
arms these gestures create
psychological barriers between you
and your audience So
you need to keep
your body open and
you're gonna come across
as a more endearing
character moving us on
to the next thing
That really baffles me
and it goes against
all the advice I
was ever taught about
presenting so most people
on YouTube when they
present they just sit
down like me right
now and this Kind
of sucks your energy
away from you and
you know, why is
it that you're doing
this? away and it
removes the ability to
use more body language
and it's less engaging
to watch. At the
end of the day
I believe most educators
are making little mini
ted talks on YouTube
and you don't see
people sat down doing
a ted talk do
you? That'd be weird.
So why is everyone
on YouTube sitting down
presenting? Well after thinking
about it it's probably
because people used to
film themselves on webcams
when you just sat
there in front of
your computer and maybe
it's just a more
chilled style but really
I think standing up
makes a lot of
sense especially in the
early days to give
you that energy so
don't think you need
to be sat down
like I am right
now ignoring all my
own advice but that's
because I've got a
five hour filming session
and I'll die otherwise.
I'd try both standing
and sitting and just
work out which version
you think you come
across better in. Dear
Mark you once told
me I gave the
worst 60 second presentation
you've ever heard. Thanks
you were right Ed.
Sometimes you just gotta
be humble. So two
quick tips before we
move on. First hand
movement. I can always
tell who's just watched
this video because their
first video out they
end up looking like
Kermit the Frog after
he's had too much
cocaine. Their arms are
like flailing super wildly
and I'm generally worried
a few of them
are flapping so much
they might take off.
Now movement is good
but if you compare
my old film booth
videos to how I
present on the Ed
Lawrence channel now you'll
see I've toned it
down a lot so
the key here is
your presenting has to
feel natural so if
you watch it back
and think oh that
looks kind of weird
look just chill out
a bit and reel
it in. Secondly when
I moved from film
booth to my current
channel I originally brought
the exact same kind
of animated video. I've
got a lot of
videos that I've never
done and I've got
a lot of videos
that I haven't done
yet so it's a
little different. I've just
been able to bring
that kind of animated
energy with me but
I had this moment
where I thought what
if this kind of
highly presented tone doesn't
match the new audience
anymore? So during my
90 -day testing period
when I posted twice
a week and tracked
things on revtrack I
tried different styles. Some
were like way more
laid back and authentic
and some were way
more planned and polished.
And I learned that
this new avatar aka
you they kind of
like less editing, less
hype,
Now, if you're an
experienced creator, you don't
need to change your
style if it's already
working, but it is
worth keeping in mind
because some audiences like
big energy, others like
Dan Coe, who makes
you wanna fall asleep
and dribble on your
arm because his voice
is so relaxing.
All right, in the
next video, I'm gonna
show you how to
edit your demo video
so that we can
get that bad mama
jammer out into the
world. Now there is
more advanced editing training
in the advanced modules,
but if I'm honest,
doing the editing yourself
is a minus 100
X move because every
hour you spend cutting
clips and putting on
B -roll and farting
around is time you
should be spending on
your business. So if
you don't have an
editor, I've got you
covered. There's a whole
outsourcing module in the
advanced modules and I've
put a list of
approved editors you can
reach out to too.
But now I want
you to go and
film that script and
then come back and
watch the next video.
Let's keep it moving,
peeps.